<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The clearing of the saints sight A sermon preached at Cundouer neere the religious and ancient towne of Shrevvsbury. By Sampson Price Batchelour of Diuinitie of Exeter Colledge in Oxford.</title>
            <author>Price, Sampson, 1585 or 6-1630.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1617</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 92 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10074</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20329</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120672</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855867</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855867</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21375</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10074)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21375)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1392:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The clearing of the saints sight A sermon preached at Cundouer neere the religious and ancient towne of Shrevvsbury. By Sampson Price Batchelour of Diuinitie of Exeter Colledge in Oxford.</title>
                  <author>Price, Sampson, 1585 or 6-1630.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 42 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by George Purslowe] for Iohn Barnes dwelling in Hosier Lane neere Smithfield,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1617.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
                  <note>Some print faded and show-through; some pages tightly bound.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21375:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21375:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CLEARING OF THE SAINTS <hi>SIGHT.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A SERMON PREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched at CVNDOVER neere the Religious and ancient Towne of SHREVVSBVRY.</p>
            <p>By SAMPSON PRICE Batchelour of <hi>Diuinitie of</hi> EXETER <hi>Colledge</hi> in OXFORD.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2. KING. 20 5.</hi>
               </bibl> I haue ſeene thy teares: Behold I will heale thee.</q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for IOHN BARNES dwelling in Hoſier Lane neere Smithfield. 1617.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21375:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21375:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, truly religious, my very good LADY, <hi>the Lady</hi> OVVEN, <hi>wife to</hi> the worthy S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> ROGER OVVEN.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ADAM: I can not more fitly ſalute you then in the phraſe of Diuine S. Iohn: <hi>Grace be with you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. ep. Ioh. 3.</note> 
               <hi>mercy and peace from God the Father, and from the Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> This <hi>Sermon</hi> prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched before you was <hi>attentiuely heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> vnto, and the copie <hi>required</hi> after the ſpeaking of it. My haſty returne from the Country to this eminent Cittie gaue me not time then to yeeld vnto that <hi>religious requeſt.</hi> But now I haue ſent it in a more publike <hi>forme,</hi> that others may receiue <hi>comfort</hi> if they haue neede of ſuch <hi>balme.</hi> I am ſure God hath prouided for euery one ſome <hi>croſſe: ELI</hi> in his <hi>children, DAVID</hi> in his <hi>enemies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dr. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll.</note> 
               <hi>IOSEPH</hi> in his <hi>brethren, LAZARVS</hi> in his <hi>body, IOHN</hi> in his <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, IOB</hi> in all.<note place="margin">Pli: hiſt: nat: l: <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> No <hi>creature</hi> commeth weeping into the world but man, and no <hi>creature</hi> weepeth ſo much being entred into the world as man. <hi>Teares</hi> are the <hi>beginning</hi> and <hi>argument</hi> of life, ſo hold ſome <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> &amp; ſome <hi>Lawyers, life</hi> by weeping, holding that if the childe were heard <hi>cry,</hi> it is a proofe of his liuing.<note place="margin">Aug: conſ: l. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> The Eyes are the <hi>chiefeſt hurt</hi> of the ſenſes, the <hi>beſt windowes</hi> for Sathan: not euill in themſelues
<pb facs="tcp:21375:3"/>but in the <hi>effects,</hi> the heart <hi>corrupting</hi> them: <hi>and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore haue teares.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr. Greenham</hi> in his counſels</note> Hearing is the ſenſe of <hi>learning,</hi> but See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is the ſenſe of <hi>certaintie.</hi> A Chriſtian compaſſed about with infirmitie may ſay as one did:<note place="margin">Greg:</note> 
               <hi>Thomas</hi> doubting hath more profited mee then <hi>Maries</hi> beleeuing, yet now <hi>if</hi> we ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,<note place="margin">Ioh: 1.46.</note> a voice will call vs, <hi>Come and ſee.</hi> Our eyes muſt bee lifted vp, for our <hi>redemption</hi> is <hi>aboue:</hi> worldly obiects dazzle the <hi>ſight</hi> in the <hi>corny</hi> vallies,<note place="margin">Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch. dial. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>airie</hi> mountaines, <hi>ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowy</hi> groues, <hi>flowrie</hi> bankes, <hi>cleare</hi> fountaines, <hi>chriſtall</hi> ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, <hi>greene</hi> meddowes, and <hi>beautifulleſt</hi> faces: as at other times in <hi>filthy</hi> dunghills, <hi>heapes</hi> of durt, <hi>miſhapen</hi> mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, <hi>rotten</hi> carrions, they are <hi>lothſome</hi> to the ſight. The ſight of the wicked to <hi>flouriſh</hi> is greenous to the godly, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard whereof <hi>Pigmelius</hi> a graue Roman Prelate, not long after the <hi>Primitiue Church</hi> being fallen <hi>blinde</hi> was wont <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>olemnely to thank <hi>God,</hi> that by that meanes he was freed from ſeeing the <hi>enemies</hi> of his Church, and eſpecially <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apoſtate. But our comfort is that our ſight ſhall be <hi>clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,</hi> and no ſuch obiects ſhall <hi>offend</hi> vs; for all occaſion of <hi>teares</hi> ſhall be taken away, and our eyes <hi>wiped</hi> with Gods owne hand. He ſhall annoint our eyes with <hi>eye-ſalue</hi> that we may ſee.<note place="margin">Rue: 3.18.</note> A toy which can not (elect Lady) be expreſſed with <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi> and <hi>inke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. ep: Io: 12.</note> but when we ſee God <hi>face</hi> to <hi>face.</hi> In the meane while our <hi>teares</hi> muſt be moderated, and we muſt waite patiently for this <hi>change.</hi> This is the aime of my poore <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations</hi> in my Sermon, and being much bounden to your <hi>worthy</hi> and <hi>learned Husband,</hi> vpon your religious deſire of the <hi>Copie,</hi> I commend it vnto your <hi>good Ladiſhip,</hi> and to all the louers of the <hi>truth</hi> who ſhall read it. And ſo leauing this <hi>memoriall</hi> of my reſpect vnto your <hi>Ladiſhip,</hi> whom I know to be <hi>zealous</hi> for the <hi>truth:</hi> with my <hi>deuotions</hi> for your honourable <hi>Husband,</hi> vertuous <hi>Selfe,</hi> and hopefull <hi>iſſue,</hi> I reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Ladiſhips in the Lord, SAMPSON PRICE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21375:3"/>
            <head>LORDIESVS BEGINNE AND <hi>END.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>REVEL: 7.17.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>God ſhall wipe away all teares from their eies.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ow glorious the <hi>nature</hi> of man was in the beginning before his fall, may appeare in his <hi>creation,</hi> GOD <hi>created man in his owne image,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 1.27.</note> Gen: 1.27. Not that he tooke vpon him an humane ſhape when hee created man; as ſome erroneouſly collected:<note place="margin">Eugubinus.</note> Neither is that <hi>image</hi> to be aſcribed onely vnto <hi>man;</hi> and the <hi>woman</hi> excluded as others defend.<note place="margin">Theodoret.</note> It was true of the male and female, they were made in <hi>Gods owne</hi> likeneſſe, which may be vnderſtood either of their <hi>dominion</hi> ouer the creatures,<note place="margin">Baſil.</note> or of their
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21375:4"/>
               <hi>immortality</hi> of the ſoule, or of their <hi>freewill:</hi> or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe as all things are originally in God,<note place="margin">Aug. l. de qu: ana: c: <hi>2.</hi> Damaſc. l: <hi>2.</hi> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ide c: <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> ſo alſo man doth participate with the nature of all <hi>crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> of <hi>plants</hi> in growing and increaſing, of <hi>beaſts</hi> inſenſe and mouing, of <hi>Angells</hi> in vnderſtanding; or rather as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh: This new man was created <hi>in righteouſnes and true holineſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 4.24.</note> Eph. 4.24. What was then wanting vnto him (ſaith <hi>Bernard</hi>) when he was ſo warmely cloathed with <hi>ſoure vertues?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ber. ſup. cant.</note> 
               <hi>Mercy</hi> kept him, <hi>Truth</hi> inſtructed him, <hi>Iuſtice</hi> ruled him, <hi>Peace</hi> nouriſhed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> him. <hi>But</hi> man being in ſuch honour forgot the goodnes of his Maker, and ſince hath remained miſerable in his poſteritie: who finding themſelues to be but men, naked, poore, and to be pittied, <hi>Iament</hi> that they are men,<note place="margin">Ber. decenſid. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>bluſh</hi> that they are naked, <hi>weepe</hi> that they are borne, and <hi>murmure</hi> that they are at all: when their <hi>bodies</hi> weake with ſickeneſſe doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member them of their mortalitie,<note place="margin">Aug. contra Iulian: l. <hi>4.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>14.</hi> &amp; <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> eſpecially when their <hi>minds</hi> are <hi>diſtracted</hi> with cares, <hi>deiected</hi> with feares, <hi>faint</hi> with labour, and <hi>addicted</hi> to pleaſures; A <hi>meditation</hi> able to make men ſinke vnder the burthen of diſcontent, <hi>if</hi> we knew not that much better things are prouided for vs hereafter. <hi>This</hi> is one part of Gods image, <hi>to bee renued in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 3.10. Exod 7.17. Oſ. 14.9. Ioh. 17.3. Ioh 1.29.</note> Col. 3. <hi>To know God to be the Lord,</hi> Exod. 7. <hi>To know him and to truſt in him,</hi> Of. 14.9. To know him to be the onely true God and Ieſus Chriſt whom he hath ſent, Ioh. 17. to know that he is the <hi>Lambe</hi> which taketh away the ſin of the world, Ioh. 1. the <hi>Lambe</hi> before whom the foure beaſts &amp; foure and twenty Elders fall downe with their
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21375:4"/>
               <hi>harpes,</hi> and golden <hi>viols</hi> full of odours; <hi>becauſe hee was worthy to take the book,</hi> and open the ſeales; <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe</hi> he was ſlaine and redeemed vs vnto God by his bloud; <hi>becauſe</hi> hee hath made vs vnto our <hi>God Kings</hi> and <hi>Prieſts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chap: 5. verſ: 8.9.13.</note> as we finde in the 5. Chapter of this Propheſie: the <hi>Lambe</hi> vnto whom euery crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture which is in <hi>heauen</hi> and on the <hi>earth,</hi> and vnder the earth, and ſuch as are in the <hi>ſea,</hi> aſcribe <hi>bleſsing, glory,</hi> and <hi>power;</hi> the <hi>Lambe</hi> who as he was carefull to charge <hi>Peter</hi> to feede his lambes,<note place="margin">Ioh 21.15.</note> Ioh. 21. ſo is he here deſcribed to prouide for his Saints in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: <hi>to aray them with white robes,</hi> that is his owne <hi>righteouſneſſe,</hi> called <hi>white raiment</hi> chap:<note place="margin">Verſ. 14.</note> 3.5. and <hi>waſhed robes</hi> made white in his owne <hi>bloud.</hi> They ſhall <hi>hunger</hi> no more, for the Lambe which is in the midſt of the <hi>throne</hi> ſhall feede them; neither <hi>thirſt</hi> any more, for he ſhall <hi>lead</hi> them vnto liuing fountaines of <hi>waters,</hi> neither ſhall the <hi>ſunne</hi> light on them, nor any <hi>heate,</hi> for <hi>God ſhall wipe away all teares from their eyes,</hi> all <hi>facultie</hi> of weeping ſhall be taken away from them.</p>
            <p>The <hi>whole Chapter</hi> containeth the eſtate of the <hi>Church</hi> to the end of the world diſtinguiſhed into <hi>two times;</hi> the <hi>firſt,</hi> wherein the true worſhippers are defined by a certaine number; the <hi>ſecond</hi> wherein they grew infinite. In the 1. verſe <hi>foure Angells</hi> hold the foure windes, <hi>by which</hi> ſome vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand <hi>Hypocrites</hi> with their impoſtures,<note place="margin">Balaus &amp; Marlor.</note> 
               <hi>Papiſts</hi> with their traditions, <hi>Tyrants</hi> with their perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and <hi>vngodly Rulers</hi> with their corruptions. <hi>Others</hi> foure bad ſpirits, of <hi>Luxurie, Pride, Gluttony,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ardens hom.</hi> Brightman in verſ: 1.</note> 
               <hi>Auarice:</hi> others foure workes of <hi>darkneſſe, conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:21375:5"/>ariſing from the <hi>Eaſt, ambition</hi> from the <hi>Weſt, hereſie</hi> from the <hi>South, Warre</hi> from the <hi>North.</hi> But <hi>if</hi> theſe were <hi>foule Angells</hi> and ready to hurt the earth by not ſuffering the <hi>Northwinde,</hi> and the <hi>Southwinde</hi> to come and blow vpon the Lords <hi>garden</hi> that the ſpices thereof might flow out,<note place="margin">Chap: 4.16.</note> that is vpon his Church to purge it from filth, and that the <hi>voice</hi> of the Turtle might not bee heard in the Land:<note place="margin">Chap. 2.12.</note> 
               <hi>neither</hi> on the <hi>Sea,</hi> that is, on conſciences which by temptations haue their ſoules melted, <hi>reeling</hi> to and fro,<note place="margin">Pſal. 107.26.</note> ſtaggering, and being at their wits end, and crying vnto the Lord, <hi>when</hi> the waues of death compaſſe them,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 22.5.6.17.</note> the flouds of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly men make them afraid, the ſorrowes of hell compaſſe them about, and the ſnares of death preuent them, till the Lord ſend from aboue, take them and draw them out of many waters: <hi>neither</hi> on any <hi>tree,</hi> that is, thoſe who are <hi>planted</hi> in the houſe of the Lord, and deſire to bring forth good fruit, and be knowne by their fruites, to bring foorth <hi>fruits</hi> meete for repentance,<note place="margin">Math. 12.33.</note> to ſpread out their <hi>roots</hi> and haue their leaues greene,<note place="margin">Math. 3.8.</note> knowing that if the tree fall toward the <hi>South,</hi> or toward the <hi>North,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 17.8.</note> in the place where it falleth there it ſhal be: If they were foule <hi>Angells,</hi> yet <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaw another Angell ſaying <hi>hurt</hi> not the earth, neither the ſea, nor the trees till wee haue ſealed the ſeruants of God in their forehead, that as <hi>God</hi> prepared an <hi>Arke</hi> for <hi>Noah</hi> and his familie before the deluge came,<note place="margin">Mr. Foot the in c. Gen. 6.</note> and as he cauſed <hi>Lot</hi> with his wife and two daughters in their lingring to bee pulled by the hand before <hi>Sodome</hi> was burnt,<note place="margin">Gen. 19.16.</note> and <hi>bloud</hi> to bee
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21375:5"/>ſprinkled vpon the two ſide poſts,<note place="margin">Exod. 12.13.</note> and on the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per doore poſt of the houſes of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> for a token that he would paſſe them ouer, and the <hi>plague</hi> ſhould not be vpon them to deſtroy them, when he ſmote the land of <hi>Aegipt:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ez 9 4.</note> and the <hi>man</hi> clothed with linnen, which had the writers <hi>inke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horne</hi> by his ſide to goe through the middeſt of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> and ſet a marke vpon the forheads of them that ſighed, before the reſt were to be ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. <hi>So here</hi> one good <hi>Angell</hi> ſuppreſſeth foure bad from executing their furie till the number were ſealed:<note place="margin">Exod. 4.23. Deut. 7.6.</note> 
               <hi>the number</hi> of all the Tribes of the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> being an hundred forty &amp; foure thouſand: twelue thouſand of the Tribe of <hi>Iuda,</hi> ſo many of <hi>Reuben, Gad, Aſſer, Nepthali, Manaſſes, Simeon, Leui, Iſſachar, Zabulon, Ioſeph</hi> and <hi>Beniamin.</hi> The <hi>Iewes</hi> were ſealed firſt becauſe Gods eldeſt Sonnes, his firſt borne, a ſpeciall people vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe aboue all people vpon the face of the earth; and after them an infinite number of other <hi>nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, kindreds, people, and tongues:</hi> all which are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, by their <hi>habit</hi> v: 9. by their <hi>doxologie</hi> v: 10. by the <hi>Angels</hi> worſhipping of God with them v: 11.12. by a <hi>Seniours</hi> queſtion v: 13. and his anſwer conteyning their deſcription. <hi>Theſe</hi> are they which came out of great tribulation v: 14. their <hi>habitation,</hi> therefore are they before the throne of God: their <hi>freedom</hi> from all euill v: 16. and their <hi>fruition</hi> of all good, when <hi>God ſhall wipe away all teares from their eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Which words</hi> of my Text are taken from a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie of <hi>Iſai:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſ 25.8.</note> one who was the moſt eloquent
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21375:6"/>
               <hi>Prophet</hi> for <hi>Hebrew</hi> in the old,<note place="margin">Ier: ep: ad Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linum.</note> as <hi>S. Paul</hi> the moſt elegant <hi>Apoſtle</hi> for <hi>Greeke</hi> in the New Teſtament: He was of the <hi>bloud Royall</hi> and brought vp at the <hi>Cour:</hi> He ſeemed rather to write a Goſpell then a Prophecie:<note place="margin">Bulli: praef. in Iſ:</note> 
               <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> and <hi>Tully</hi> come ſhort of him in their Orations. <hi>He</hi> deſcribeth the ioyes of the elect by a <hi>banquet</hi> Iſ: 25. that as God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pareth a <hi>table</hi> for vs here in the <hi>ſcripture,</hi> where is <hi>doctrinalis ſapientia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bertrand: in Eua: Dom: <hi>2.</hi> poſt Pentecoſt.</note> and in the Church where there is <hi>ſacramentalis Euchariſtia,</hi> and in the deuout ſoule where is <hi>ſpiritualis laetitia,</hi> ſo hereafter a table in glory, where is <hi>immortalis ſufficientia.</hi> In this life he feaſteth vs with <hi>doctrine</hi> in the wiſdome of the word, with <hi>thankſgiuing</hi> in the Sacraments, and ioy in the ſpirit; <hi>but</hi> there is no true ſufficiency till wee come to the mountaine where the <hi>Lord</hi> ſhall make vnto all people a <hi>feaſt</hi> of fat things, a feaſt of wine on the lees, of fat things full of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, of <hi>wine</hi> on the lees well refined: he will ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low vp death in victorie, and <hi>wipe away teares from all faces,</hi> and the rebuke of his people: <hi>God ſhall wipe away all teares from their eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>ſumme</hi> of which words is an <hi>aſſurance</hi> that God will one day take away all occaſion of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and fill his with perfect ioy.<note place="margin">Gen: Note in Iſ: <hi>25.</hi> Ribera.</note> 
               <hi>Or</hi> here wee learne that howſoeuer this world be a valley of <hi>teares,</hi> yet we ſhall haue a place of reioyeing. It is a <hi>ſimilitude</hi> from mothers,<note place="margin">Viegas &amp; Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonius.</note> who when their little children cry, giue vnto them faire ſpeeches, em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace them, and wipe their faces: can a <hi>woman</hi> forget her ſucking child, that ſhe ſhould not haue compaſſion on the ſonne of her wombe? <hi>Yea,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:21375:6"/>they may forget, yet will I not forget thee.<note place="margin">Iſ. 49.15.</note> Iſ: 49 <hi>As</hi> one whom his mother comforteth, ſo will I comfort you, and yee ſhall be comforted in Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem. Iſ: 66.<note place="margin">Iſ. 66.13.</note> 
               <hi>God ſhall wipe away all teares from their eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that we may call this ſcripture, <hi>The Mourners reward,</hi> or <hi>The glorifying of the eyes,</hi> or <hi>The clearing of the Saints ſight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which obſerue
<list>
                  <item>1. The <hi>Author</hi> of this comfort who he is, <hi>God.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. The <hi>Act</hi> what he doth, <hi>ſhall wipe away all teares.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. The <hi>obiect</hi> to bee cleared, <hi>from their eyes.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt conteineth him that is <hi>ſummum bonum</hi> the chiefe good.</p>
            <p>The ſecond remoueth <hi>ſummum malu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt miſery, weeping and gnaſhing of teeth.</p>
            <p>The third cureth <hi>ſtillantem oculum,</hi> the drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping eye.</p>
            <p>In the firſt we haue a powerfull and omnipotent <hi>Maieſty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſecond, a ready and willing helpe in the greateſt <hi>extremity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the third, a mauifeſt and cleare aſſurance of glory.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the <hi>bounds</hi> which confine my medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations: Hee that hath <hi>eyes</hi> to ſee let him watch, and euery one that euer had any portion of true ſorrow, let him ſo learne that he may goe away with that liuery of the diſciples: <hi>Bleſſed are they that mourne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 5.4.</note> 
               <hi>for they ſhall be comforted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:21375:7"/>When <hi>Origen</hi> a man of immortall wit,<note place="margin">Ier: catal: &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>apol: adu: Ruff: Orig: hom: <hi>7.</hi> in Ioſ.</note> &amp; moſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in all ſecular knowledge, whoſe knowledge of the ſcriptures <hi>Ierom</hi> wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred at, was to expound the word <hi>Iubilate,</hi> he profeſſed that he felt himſelfe inwardly touched, hee knew not by whatſecret &amp; extraordinary motion, to ſearch into the ſecret meaning of it, hoping there to find, as <hi>Chryſostome</hi> ſpake in another caſe,<note place="margin">Chryſ. hom. <hi>15.</hi> in Gen.</note> 
               <hi>Theſaurum magnum in parua dictione,</hi> ſome great treaſure couched in that litle word: <hi>I am ſure</hi> there is no word more full of ſtore then the name of <hi>God</hi> here, in Greeke <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, rendred by <hi>Beza</hi> and <hi>Tremelius</hi> Deus: <hi>Ludouicus Viues</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued truly,<note place="margin">De veritacefi. le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. l: <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> that Iudaiſme and Mahometiſme, and all other ſuperſtitious deuotions are but like vnto the glaſſe which is brittle and cannot endure the hammer, but the <hi>Chriſtian faith</hi> is like the gold, whether melted, or rubbed, or beaten it ſtill ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the more orient: ſo is the doctrine of the true <hi>God,</hi> it feareth not the touchſtone, but hath medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation enough in it to buſie the curiouſeſt ſearcher of the world: A <hi>miſtery</hi> which made <hi>Triſmegiſtus</hi> call <hi>God</hi> ineffable,<note place="margin">Triſmeg. ad Tatium.</note> one that could not be pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and the Iewes ſo ſuperſtitious that they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed this name to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enarrable; ineffable, not to be expreſſed: and <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nobius</hi> that <hi>Qui ſe putat magnitudinem Deinoſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Arnob. l: <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>minuit,</hi> He that thinketh he knoweth the greatnes of God, leſſeneth it as much as he may. It is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to know his eſſence: He hath neede of the <hi>Logique</hi> of God himſelfe that ſhould giue a perfect definition of him;<note place="margin">M: Cartwr: ca tech. p. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> yet how much haue many laboured in this ſecret? The <hi>Rabbines</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21375:7"/>that the name <hi>Iehouah</hi> hath foure letters of reſt, to ſignifie that the reſt and tranquillitie of all the creatures in the world is in God alone: <hi>Steuchus</hi> thinking that none can interpret it; <hi>Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Burgenſis</hi> that none can tranſlate it: <hi>Zanchius</hi> and others, that it is a name of 4 letters in all lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages; in the Roman <hi>Deus,</hi> the Spaniſh <hi>Dios,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zan. de natura Dei, l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> the Italian IDIO, the French <hi>Dieu,</hi> the German <hi>Gott,</hi> the Perſian <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Magi pronouncing it <hi>Orſi,</hi> the Dalmatians <hi>Bogi,</hi> the Mahumetans <hi>Abgd,</hi> the new found world <hi>Zimi,</hi> the Aſſirians <hi>Adad,</hi> the Aegiptians <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Arabians <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Hetruſci <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as if they knew that God is not the God of the Iewes only, but of all the world beſides. His name is I AM,<note place="margin">Exod. 3.14.</note> 
               <hi>Exod.</hi> 3. importing the eternitie of his eſſence, the ſame yeſterday, and to day,<note place="margin">Heb. 13.8.</note> and for euer, and the exiſtence and perfection of all things in him, <hi>Non quòd illa ſunt quod eſt ille, ſed quia ex ipſo,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ber. in Cant. ſer. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> Not that they are the ſame that he is, but becauſe of him, and through him, and to him are all things. Therefore did <hi>Plato</hi> call him <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that which is:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom. 11.36.</hi> Zan. de natura Dei, l. <hi>1.</hi> c <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> and in his <hi>Timae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> reprehendeth thoſe which attribute vnto him either the future or the preterperfect tenſe, foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as neither of thoſe tenſes did agree with him, but the preſent tenſe only. Therefore <hi>Thales</hi> anſwered, being demanded what God was: <hi>Quod principio &amp; fine caret,</hi> That which wanteth begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and ending. And vpon the doores of the Temple of <hi>Delphas</hi> the inſcription was in capitall letters E I, <hi>veram, certam,<note place="margin">Plut. mor. part. <hi>1.</hi> de <hi>E I</hi> apud Delphos.</note> ſolam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſoli conuenientem ei appellationem qua eſſe dicitur, tribuentes;</hi> giuing
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21375:8"/>him thereby a true, a certaine, and only appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of exiſting alone.<note place="margin">Gr Naz Orat. <hi>38.</hi>
               </note> This name <hi>Nazranzene</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led an infinite and boundleſſe <hi>Ocean:</hi> and <hi>Auſtin</hi> tels vs, <hi>Quo intellectu Deum capit homo qui ipſum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectum ſuum quo cum vult capere nondum capit?</hi> With what vnderſtanding can man poſſibly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue God, who cannot conceiue his owne vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding? Yet becauſe <hi>Eſt in Deo quod percipi poteſt, ſi quod poteſt velis;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hil. de Trin. l. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> There is in God that which may bee perceiued by vs, if wee endeuour that which may be; as there is in the <hi>Sunne</hi> that which may be ſeene, if wee will ſee what we may: but often men loſe what they may ſee, if they endeuour to ſee more then they may ſee. Let vs looke vpon his workes,<note place="margin">Dionyſ. de diu. nom. c. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> for <hi>Dei nomen mirabile nomen, ſuper om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne nomen, ſed ſine nomine;</hi> The name of God is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable, aboue euery name, not to bee expreſſed by any name. Were all the land paper, and all the water inke, euery plant a pen, and euery other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture a ſwift and readie Scribe, they could not ſet downe the leaſt peece of his greatneſſe. Hee is <hi>length</hi> in reſpect of eternitie,<note place="margin">Ber. de conſid.</note> 
               <hi>breadth</hi> in regard of charitie, <hi>height</hi> for his maieſtie, <hi>depth</hi> for his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. He hath much more then the Poet found in <hi>Iupiter.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Eſtque Dei ſedes, vbi terra, &amp; pontus, &amp; aer,</l>
               <l>Et coelum,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lucanus</hi> 9.</note> &amp; virtus, ſuperos: quid quaerimus vltra?</l>
               <l>Iupiter eſt quodcunque vides, quocunque moueris.</l>
            </q>
            <p>He hath <hi>Heauen</hi> for his throne,<note place="margin">Matt. 5.34 35. 1. King. 8 27.</note> and the <hi>Earth</hi> for his footſtoole, nay behold the heauen and heauen of heauens cannot containe him: there is not an hearbe, flower, tree, leafe, ſeede, fruit, beaſt or
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21375:8"/>worme, wherein wee ſee not the power of his <hi>Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</hi> All Thrones are but pieces of his footſtoole: hee is a <hi>God</hi> before whom there was no God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, neither ſhall there be after him; the <hi>Lord,</hi> and beſides him there is no <hi>Sauiour.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſ. 43.10.11.13.</note> Hee will worke, and who can let it? Here is the <hi>Sphynx</hi> of diuinitie, if I may ſo call it, to looke vpon this Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie vnto whom the <hi>Rabbins</hi> haue giuen three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore and ten names diuerſified in ten ſorts, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in all ſeuen hundred and twenty names; but I muſt confeſſe as <hi>Iuſtin Martyr</hi> did,<note place="margin">Iuſt. Mart. l. <hi>1.</hi> confeſſ fidei.</note> that it is a <hi>my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie</hi> which is rather to be receiued by faith then conceiued by reaſon: yet as men when they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to ſee the <hi>Sunne</hi> in an inter poſition doe looke into the water, and as that <hi>Geometrician,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lipſ. polit.</note> finding the length of <hi>Hercules</hi> foot vpon the hill <hi>Olympus,</hi> gheſſed at the proportion of his whole body, and becauſe howſoeuer the diuine nature be in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible, yet we ſhould not wholly deſiſt from ſearching it,<note place="margin">Iuſt. Mart. de Trin.</note> conſuming our time in idleneſſe; we muſt looke vpon <hi>God</hi> in his <hi>workes,</hi> and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that he is a <hi>God of Gods,</hi> and Lord of Lords, a great <hi>God,</hi> a mighty and terrible, <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.<note place="margin">Deut. 10.17. Mar. 27. 1. Cor. 8.6. Rom. 15.5.</note> a <hi>God</hi> only forgiuing ſinnes, <hi>Mark.</hi> 2. one <hi>God</hi> of whom are all things and we in him, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. <hi>the God of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and conſolation, Rom.</hi> 15. <hi>here</hi> comforting his Church after their tribulations, hungring, thirſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and weeping: whence we may be directed to this vſefull <hi>obſeruation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That God is the Author of the only and true comfort vnto his ſeruants.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Doct.</note>
            </p>
            <p>A <hi>truth</hi> confirmed plentifully in the <hi>Scriptures.</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:21375:9"/>This was the encouragement that the Lord gaue vnto <hi>Iſaac</hi> when hee appeared vnto him, either awake as ſome hold,<note place="margin">Lippoma. Toſlat.</note> or aſleepe as others: <hi>I am the God of Abraham thy father, feare not, for I am with thee, and will bleſſe thee, and multiplie thy ſeede for my ſeruant Abrahams ſake,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 26.24.</note> 
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 26. The <hi>Heathens</hi> had their nationall Gods which were no Gods, the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyrians <hi>Belus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Peter in Gen.</note> the Aegyptians <hi>Iſis,</hi> the Tyrians <hi>Baal,</hi> the Athenians <hi>Minerua,</hi> the Samians <hi>Iuno,</hi> the Lemnians <hi>Vulcan,</hi> the Romans <hi>Quirinus,</hi> &amp;c. But our <hi>God</hi> is the peculiar God of <hi>Abraham</hi> and of the faithfull.<note place="margin">Gen. 28.15.</note> Hee thus heartned <hi>Iacob, Gen.</hi> 28. I am with thee, and will keepe thee in all places whither thou goeſt, I will not leaue thee: ſo he promiſed, <hi>Gen.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 46.4.</note> 46. I will goe downe with thee into Aegypt, and I will alſo ſuroly bring thee vp againe: which was performed when his body was carried to bee buried in <hi>Canaan</hi> as he had charged <hi>Ioſeph</hi> with an oath,<note place="margin">Gen. 47.31.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe</hi> that was the place which the Lord choſe for his people to dwell in; or the <hi>Patriarchs</hi> deſired to be buried in the land of promiſe to teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie their faith that God would bring their ſeed thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: <hi>or</hi> as hauing the ſame hope of the <hi>reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> or <hi>foreſeeing</hi> that the Meſſiah ſhould be borne there; but moſt of all the <hi>promiſe</hi> was performed in his ſeed, whom the Lord brought out of <hi>Aegypt</hi> vnder the hand of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron. God</hi> killeth and maketh aliue,<note place="margin">Deut 32.39.</note> woundeth and healeth, <hi>Deu.</hi> 32. <hi>Hee</hi> giueth the former and the latter raine,<note place="margin">Ioel 2.23.</note> 
               <hi>Ioel</hi> 2. <hi>Except</hi> hee build the houſe, they labour in vaine that build it:<note place="margin">Pſal. 1 27 1.</note> no houſe is a fortreſſe if vnarmed of this weapon,<note place="margin">ſer. 22.15.</note> though of Cedar. Excopt he keepe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21375:9"/>the Citie, the watchman waketh but in vaine. <hi>Doth</hi> a man eat and drinke, and make his ſoule en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy good in his labour?<note place="margin">Eccl. 2.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>This is from the hand of God.</hi> How many haue varieties of meats, and cannot eat, being troubled with a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that when they are chaſtened with paine vpon their beds, and the multitude of their bones with ſtrong paine, their life abhorreth bread,<note place="margin">Iob 33.19.20.</note> and their ſoule daintie meat? <hi>How many</hi> haue beene ſlaine as the <hi>Amalekites</hi> while they were ſpread abroad vpon the earth, eating, and drinking, and dancing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of all the great ſpoile that they had taken?<note place="margin">1. Sam 30.16.</note> 
               <hi>Hane</hi> men <hi>riches,</hi> and wealth, and the power there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, to take their portion and reioyce in their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour? <hi>This is the gift of God;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl 5.19. Iob 21.16.</note> 
               <hi>others</hi> gather ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to their owne hurt, <hi>vel inde ſuperbiendo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hago.</note> 
               <hi>vel non praeſtando, &amp;c.</hi> either growing proud by them, or not being good ſtewards of them, not ſuffering them to ſleepe, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.12. being as much troubled to keepe them as euer to get them, fearing <hi>loſſes,</hi> or thinking vpon vnlawfull <hi>gaine</hi> by <hi>vſurie,</hi> and other ſore euils.<note place="margin">Amb. in Pſ. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> Haue men beene preſerued from their enemies, and triumphed in the victorie? God teacheth their hands to warre and fingers to fight. <hi>God</hi> made all, and ruleth all;<note place="margin">Pſal. 144 1. <hi>Chryſ.</hi>
               </note> and as a <hi>ſhip</hi> without a gouernour is for no ſeruice, as a <hi>bodie</hi> without a ſoule of no power, ſo the <hi>World</hi> could neuer be created as it was, nor continue as it is, nor come to that it is to be, without this God. No being, no liuing, no comfort is without him. He worketh ſometimes <hi>without meanes,</hi> as hee created
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21375:10"/>the world of nothing in the beginning, not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue any happineſſe by the things created,<note place="margin">Aug. de gen. co. plan. c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the which hee was happy, but hee made the world to manifeſt his glory and declare his mercy: ſo without meanes hee preſerued <hi>Moſes</hi> on the mount forty dayes and forty nights,<note place="margin">Exod. 34 28.</note> hee did nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eat bread nor drinke water;<note place="margin">Deut. 29 5.</note> he led the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites forty yeeres in the wilderneſſe, their clothes and ſhooes not waxing old: ſo often in <hi>tempeſts</hi> at ſea when men looke euery houre to be caſt away, when the <hi>keele</hi> be it neuer ſo ſtrong, the <hi>ribs</hi> be they neuer ſo ſtiffe, the <hi>cleets</hi> and clamps of iron be they neuer ſo faſt ſet on, are like to flie in peeces, or if a <hi>ioynt</hi> cracke all is hazarded, if a <hi>planke</hi> ſhoot vp, all is like to be gone, when they mount vp to heauen, and goe downe againe to the depths,<note place="margin">Pſal. 107.</note> their ſoule being melted becauſe of trouble, they reele to and fro, and ſtagger like a drunken man, and are at their wits end, <hi>God</hi> maketh the ſtorme a calme; ſo in extremitie of ſickneſſe, when <hi>Phyſitians</hi> and all giue a man off,<note place="margin">Iob 16.2.</note> that he crieth out as <hi>Iob, Miſerable comforters are ye all:</hi> in dangerous <hi>childbirths,</hi> when women haue with <hi>Rachel</hi> hard labour,<note place="margin">Gen. 35.16.</note> and in other extremities when we ſee no meanes of helpe in the world, God commenth in with his helping hand, and maketh the waues ſtill, turneth deadly ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe into a ſafe recouerie, ſorrowfull trauailes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ioyfull deliueries, bitterneſſe into ſweetneſſe, and that immediately.</p>
            <p>God worketh <hi>comfort ſometimes againſt meanes,</hi> as when the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> paſſed ouer vpon the drie ground in the midſt of the ſea, and the waters
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21375:10"/>were a wall vnto them on their right hand and on<note place="margin">Exod. 14 22.</note> their left, <hi>Exod.</hi> 14. in the diuiſion of <hi>Iordan</hi> for <hi>Elijah,</hi> in the ſtanding ſtill of the <hi>Sunne</hi> for <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> in the not burning of the <hi>three children,</hi> in the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry <hi>Lions</hi> not deuouring <hi>Daniel,</hi> in the <hi>Viper</hi> not hurting <hi>S. Paul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sometimes God worketh <hi>by meanes,</hi> as by <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,</hi> appearing either viſibly as they did to <hi>Iacob</hi> when he went on his way,<note place="margin">Gen. 32.1.</note> which hee called Gods hoſt; or not ſeene at the firſt, but afterwards, as <hi>Eliſha</hi> praying that his ſeruants eyes might be ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and behold the mountaine was full of horſes, and chariots of fire round about <hi>Eliſha,</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 6. which were Angels:<note place="margin">2. King. 6.17.</note> or moſt commonly not <hi>ſeene</hi> to men, yet alwayes in a readineſſe for Gods ſeruice and his childrens preſeruation, encamping round about them that feare him,<note place="margin">Pſal. 34.7.</note> and deliuering them, being all miniſtring ſpirits ſent forth to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter for them who ſhall be heires of ſaluation.<note place="margin">Heb. 1.14.</note> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides theſe, God comforteth men <hi>with his other creatures,</hi> thoſe two great lights, the <hi>Sunne</hi> to rule by day, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 136.8. which <hi>Anaxagoras</hi> held much greater then <hi>Peloponeſus</hi> a countrey in <hi>Graecia, Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ximander</hi> as bigge as the earth, the <hi>Mathematicians</hi> exceeding the earth 166. times:<note place="margin">Clauius.</note> the <hi>Moone</hi> to rule the night;<note place="margin">Iob 38.31.32.</note> ſuch are the influences of <hi>Pleiades</hi> brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the ſpring, the bands of <hi>Orion</hi> bringing raine, <hi>Mazzaroth</hi> in his ſeaſon, and <hi>Arcturus</hi> with his ſonnes. Hee heareth the heauens, they heare the earth, and the earth ſhall heare the corne,<note place="margin">Oſ. 2.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and the wine, and the oile. He is with <hi>Kings</hi> is their king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, <hi>Biſhops</hi> in their churches, <hi>Peeres</hi> in their
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21375:11"/>conſultations, <hi>Iudges</hi> in their iudgements, <hi>Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines</hi> in their battels, euer ready to comfort when the helpe of man is vaine.<note place="margin">Iſ. 50.3.</note> He that can cloath the <hi>heauens</hi> with blackneſſe, and make ſackcloth their couering, can alſo ſtretch them out like a <hi>curtaine</hi> to couer himſelfe with light as with a garment. He that can ſend out a great <hi>winde</hi> into the <hi>Sea</hi> till it worke and be tempeſtuous,<note place="margin">Pſal 104.2. Io. 1.4.11.</note> and the <hi>waues</hi> thereof toſſe themſelues,<note place="margin">Ier. 5.22.</note> can alſo ſtay them that they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile not thought they rore and ſmite through the pride thereof. <hi>Inſtrumenta ſunt tota creatura Dei,</hi> all the creatures of God are ready at his command to attend the elect for their good,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob 26 12.</hi> Wigand. Syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tag. V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. Teſt.</note> and the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate for their hurt. He is the beſt <hi>comforter:</hi> others may deceiue, a <hi>friend</hi> his friend, as <hi>Achitophel</hi> did <hi>Dauid,</hi> a <hi>Counſeller</hi> his client, as <hi>Abimelech</hi> the <hi>Sche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chemits,</hi> the <hi>wife</hi> the husband, as <hi>Dalilah</hi> did <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> the <hi>daughter</hi> leaue <hi>the mother,</hi> as <hi>Orpah Naomi:</hi> but God neuer faileth; and therefore as <hi>Demoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henes</hi> held that no man could be miſerable which laid temperance and continencie for a foundation of wiſdome; ſo much more may wee hold him to be moſt comforted which hath the Lord for his God; and as that Emperour <hi>Marcus Aurelius</hi> often profeſſed, that hee would not leaue the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge hee might learne in one houre for all the gold hee poſſeſſed, receiuing more glory from the bookes hee read and wrote, then all the battels he wonne and kingdomes he conquered, ſo may wee reſolue that this only maketh vs happy, that God doth comfort vs.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vſe.</hi> 1.</note>How <hi>wretched</hi> then is the eſtate of them which
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21375:11"/>oppoſe themſelues againſt this <hi>God</hi> of <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort.</hi> Such are the <hi>Atheiſts</hi> of this age, whoſe Patron was <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: in plaine termes denying that there was any God at all, and <hi>Epicurus</hi> trampling vpon religion: They are <hi>Infidels</hi> in heart, <hi>Blaſphemers</hi> in tongue, the greateſt <hi>Traitors</hi> to their Prince, <hi>Rebels</hi> to their country, a poyſon to their houſes, plague to their friends: cauſing the <hi>earth</hi> vpon which they goe to be curſed, the <hi>ayre</hi> where they ſpeake, to be infected, and <hi>Sathan</hi> where they enter to be poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Strange it is, that eyther <hi>Graecian</hi> or <hi>Barbarian, Turke</hi> or <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> any one whoſe ſeet tread vpon the earth, or whoſe eyelids are opened towards heauen, ſhould not in their liues proclaime the comfortable Maieſty of this God: but as it is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed that <hi>Anaxagoras</hi> would neuer haue affirmed ſnow to be blacke, but that he was ſtarke blinde of both his eyes: ſo theſe would neuer ſo much erre, but that they are blinded in their vnderſtanding; more inſenſible then the creatures voyd of reaſon; for the <hi>ſtarre</hi> confeſſed the ſon of God, and led the wiſe men to <hi>Chriſt;</hi> the <hi>ſea</hi> and windes did obey him: the <hi>Aſſe</hi> did beare him to Ieruſalem: the <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes</hi> at his command came into the net, and one brought money to pay tribute: the <hi>Sunne</hi> at his death was appalled, the earth did tremble, the <hi>ſtones</hi> did cleaue aſunder, and the <hi>graues</hi> did open: they are more obſtinate then the Deuill,<note place="margin">Mar. 5.6.7.</note> ſeeing <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> a farre off, he came and worſhipped him, crying with a loud voice, that hee was the Sonne of the moſt high God: <hi>Ieſus</hi> hee knoweth and <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 19 15.</note> but theſe acknowledge neyther <hi>God</hi> nor <hi>Ieſus,</hi> nor any
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21375:12"/>true Prophets ſent from God, but the time ſhall come that <hi>the eyes that ſinne hath ſhut, damnation ſhall open,</hi> and they ſhall know that this God is not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitly called by the Graecians <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for the ſharpneſſe of his ſight, and ſwiftneſſe of his courſe, ſeeing all, and ruling ouer all in a moment, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by all things are cauſed to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for that he giueth life and motion to all,<note place="margin">Ariſted: in hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no in Iouem. Diog. La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. c. el: Rhodig.</note> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in reguard of his goodnes: whither ſhould I ſend the fooliſh <hi>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals</hi> which neuer look vpon the God of Nature, but to the <hi>creatour</hi> of all, which faſhioned all. <hi>Nature</hi> it ſelfe is nothing but a power placed by this God in his creatures.<note place="margin">Hugo.</note> 
               <hi>Quis diſpoſuit membra pulicis &amp; cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licis,</hi> who hath diſpoſed in order the limmes of the flea and gnat, they haue their life and motion, fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing death, louing life, ſeeking after that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in, ſhunning that which troubleth them, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſenſe and quickneſſe in motion. This God made them: <hi>Qui fecit Angelumin coelo fecit vermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum infecta:</hi> He that made the Angell in Heauen made the little worine on the earth:<note place="margin">Aug ſuper. Pſal. <hi>148.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Totum attende, totum lauda,</hi> conſider all the order of Gods workes, thou ſhalt ſee cauſe enough to praiſe God for all: Thou art without excuſe, for the inuiſible things of him from the creation of the world are cleerely ſeene being vnderſtood by the things that are made.<note place="margin">Rom. 1.20.</note> 
               <hi>Witneſſes</hi> againſt thee ſhall be, that the <hi>Lord</hi> hath done good for thee and giuen thee rain from heauen, and fruitfull ſeaſons, filling thy heart with food and gladnes, beſide the expreſſe <hi>teſtimonies</hi> of the word,<note place="margin">Acts 14 17.</note> open <hi>prophecies</hi> of things to come thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of yeeres before they came, and infinite <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles:</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:21375:12"/>O reaſon not as the beſotted <hi>Epicure:</hi> How doth God know, can hee iudge through the darke clouds?<note place="margin">Iob 22.13.</note> thicke clouds are a couering to him that he ſeeth not, and he walketh in the circuit of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: God is euery where, and there is no euaſion from him, no corner in hell, no manſion in heauen, no caue in the top of <hi>Carmel,</hi> no fiſhes belly in the bottome of the Sea, no dark dungeon in the land of captiuity, no clouds of the day, darkneſſe of the night, ſecrecie of a friend, or a more ſecret conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, nor any like euaſion can hide thee or thy acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from this God. He maketh the <hi>fields</hi> haue eyes to ſee thy deeds, the <hi>woods</hi> eares to heare our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, the <hi>wals</hi> of our bed chambers mouths to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe againſt vs. He can vſe thy ſelfe as an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt thy ſelfe, and thine owne mouth to teſtifie againſt thee, eyther vnawares to <hi>diſcloſe</hi> thy faults, or in ſleepe by a <hi>dreame</hi> to make them knowne, or in ſickneſſe to <hi>raue</hi> at the ſight of them, or elſe in ſome <hi>phrenſie</hi> to vomit them out, or in the torment of <hi>conſcience</hi> to confeſſe them all. To the wicked this <hi>God</hi> at the laſt day ſhall appeare terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, his <hi>face</hi> as a flame of fire, his <hi>voice</hi> thunder, his <hi>wrath</hi> horror. He ſhall meet them riding vpon the wings of the winde, raining vpon them <hi>ſnares</hi> to entrap them, <hi>fire</hi> to deuoure them, <hi>hailstones</hi> to kil them, a <hi>ſmoke</hi> to ſmother them, a ſtormy tempeſt to terrifie them, the ſtinck of <hi>brimſtone</hi> to annoy them, and hot <hi>thunder bolts</hi> to ſhoot them thorow, &amp; then ſend them to the great gaole of hell, where there is no deſire but reuenge, no deuotion but curſing, no bleſſing, but blaſphemy where they
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21375:13"/>may be remooued from place to place, but neuer eyther be eaſed of pangs or freed of paines: where there ſhall be <hi>famine</hi> for gluttony, <hi>thirst</hi> for drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe, <hi>burning</hi> for luſt, <hi>madneſſe</hi> for ſwearing, <hi>want</hi> for ill gotten goods, <hi>ſtaruing</hi> for cruelty. But to the elect hee ſhall bring ioy, peace, and all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.28.</note> Hee ſhall be all in all to them.</p>
            <p>How ſhould this encourage vs now to be known to this <hi>God</hi> of comfort,<note place="margin">Vſe.</note> to beleeue him to be, and to conceiue him rightly, to remember his preſence and conſider his prouidence: to loue him aboue all to hold on his ſide againſt all, and to be ſubiect to him before all. He <hi>foreſeeth</hi> all our troubles be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they be, wiſely ordereth them, and <hi>preordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth</hi> what ſhall be the end. O that all were ſo wiſe to conſider and thinke vpon this, then would not ſome in a deſperate diſcontent make their owne hands their <hi>executioners, others</hi> vpon <hi>croſſes</hi> be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried violently from their wits, <hi>others</hi> euer be wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for <hi>death,</hi> though vnprepared for it, <hi>others</hi> mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure againſt God becauſe their reward is not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe for ſeruing God, <hi>others</hi> vpon a ſting of conſcience ſeeke for merry and prophane compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, ſumptuous and rioting feaſts, reuelling and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull games, wanton &amp; vnchaſt ſongs, the ſound only of the <hi>viol</hi> and <hi>harpe</hi> to driue away care, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as earth can neuer redreſſe that which came from Heauen. Expect of thy <hi>ſtepmother</hi> nothing but diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content. The world is an <hi>ocean</hi> of troubles, here is no firme land, miſchiefes muſt ſtriue for places leſt they loſe their roomes; Hee ſeeketh vs that made vs, let vs not bite the ſtone, but look vp to the hand,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21375:13"/>and then as <hi>Moſes</hi> feared not his rod though it were turned into a ſerpent,<note place="margin">Exod. 7.9.</note> no more ſhal we all the crau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and hiſſing ſcourges of this life. Doth any now droop vnder a feigned cuill, or augment ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row through impatience, or feare danger yet farre off, or being diſtracted with the paſſions of the mind and haunted with ſin, ſit downe and weepe, and refuſe comfort contrary to that rule;</p>
            <q>Fortianimo mala fer, nec bis miſer eſto dolore.</q>
            <p>Behold here is a <hi>cordiall, Aquacaeleſtis,</hi> water from heauen, a preſeruatiue againſt the poyſon of any diſcontent: other helps may make vs like glow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wormes, which caſt a fire, but being preſſed, there is nothing but a crude moiſture; they are ſeeming and only ſhining comforts, but God is a true and onely comforter; hee comforted <hi>Dauid</hi> when hee was weary with groaning,<note place="margin">I ſai 6.6. Iſa. 38.14,</note> 
               <hi>Iſai</hi> when hee chattered like a Crane, or Swallow, mourned like a Doue, &amp; his eyes failed with looking vpward,<note place="margin">Iob. 42.6.</note> 
               <hi>Iob</hi> when hee abhorred himſelfe, and repented in duſt and aſhes; <hi>Manaſſes</hi> when hee was taken among the theeues,<note place="margin">2 Chro. 33.11 Pſal. 42.5.</note> bound with fetters, and carried to <hi>Babylon:</hi> Why then ſhould we caſt downe our ſoules and bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted within vs: wee ſhould rather imitate <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> that heroike ſpirit, who when the world ſtood againſt him, he cauſed that Pſalme to be ſung, the title whereof is:<note place="margin">Pſal. 46.1.</note> 
               <hi>The confidence which the Church hath in God: God</hi> is our refuge and ſtrength, a very preſent helpe in trouble: wee ſhould bee glad and reioyce in the <hi>Lord</hi> our <hi>God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lel. 2.23.</note> and as the <hi>Hart</hi> pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth after the water-brookes, ſo ſhould our ſoules pant after God,<note place="margin">Pſal. 42 1.</note> for hee hath not onely annointed
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:21375:14"/>others to <hi>preach</hi> good tidings vnto the meek, to <hi>bind</hi> vp the broken-hearted, to <hi>proclaime</hi> liberty to the captiues,<note place="margin">Iſa. 61.</note> and the opening of the priſon to them that are bound, but he himſelfe looketh vppon the mourners in <hi>Zion,</hi> giuing vnto them <hi>beauty</hi> for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, the <hi>oyle</hi> of ioy for mourning, the <hi>garment</hi> of praiſe for the ſpirit of heauineſſe, and <hi>hee ſhall wipe away all teares from their eyes:</hi> It is his owne Act, which is my ſecond part.</p>
            <p>THE true <hi>Church</hi> out of which there is no ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pars.</hi> 2.</note> is compared to many glorious things to a <hi>Doue</hi> for her louelineſſe, to a <hi>Vine</hi> for her fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, to a <hi>mount</hi> for her ſafeneſſe, to a <hi>Prieſthood</hi> for her holineſſe, to a <hi>Queene</hi> for her royalty, to a <hi>Tower</hi> for her gliſtring; yet ſhe doth but ſoiorne, and while it is vpon earth, is ſubiect to the ſcorch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſun: the whole world is but a low moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh watry ground, and the <hi>Elect</hi> heere are like the children of Iſraell, lifting vp their voyces and wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping becauſe they are in <hi>Bochim:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>: Tremel. Iud. <hi>2.5.</hi>
               </note> i. a place full of weepers, they are vſually eyther in blacks mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, or in <hi>red</hi> perſecuted, yet glorious in this ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell,<note place="margin">Iſa. 63.</note> trauelling in the greatneſſe of their ſtrength being dipt in bloud.</p>
            <p>This life is a ſeede-time and wil be louring, <hi>Poſt nubila ſudum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reuel. 19.13.</note> we ſhall haue a calme harueſt. Wee are <hi>trauellers,</hi> and ſhall vſe many hoſts though wee ſhall finde few friends: our daies are ſpent eyther in ſeeing or doing or ſuffering euill.<note place="margin">Greg: Naz.</note> Euery one hath his <hi>roule</hi> ſpread before him written within
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21375:14"/>and without; <hi>Lamentations,</hi> and <hi>mourning,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ez 2 10.</note> and <hi>woe:</hi> ſome put ſinging for mourning, ſo that teares ſometimes may haue reioycing, as <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſpeaketh of ſome, <hi>Gaudium pectoris lachrymis expri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vulg carmen.</note> they expreſſed the ioy of their hearts by their teares:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cyp</hi> Gen 43.30.</note> ſuch were the teares of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſeeing his brother <hi>Beniamin,</hi> his only brother by the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſide, his bowels did yerne, and hee ſought where to weepe, and hee entred into his chamber and vvept there:<note place="margin">Iunius.</note> ſuch were the teares of <hi>Iacob</hi> when <hi>Ioſeph</hi> made ready his chariot and went to meet him to <hi>Goſhen</hi> in the City of the Nobles,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Septuag.</hi> Gen. 46.29.</note> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented himſelfe vnto him, he fell on his necke and wept on his necke a good while; ſo did that father at the returne of a <hi>prodigall, Luk.</hi> 15.20. but vſually teares are the <hi>iuice</hi> of a minde preſſed with griefe. The <hi>father</hi> weepeth for the death of his <hi>ſonne,</hi> as <hi>Dauid</hi> for <hi>Abſolon</hi> as hee went vp to the chamber ouer the gate,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 18.33</note> as if like <hi>Aeneas</hi> hee had cared for none elſe but <hi>Abſolon.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Omnis in Aſcanio chari ſlat cura parentis.<note place="margin">Virg.</note>
            </q>
            <p>O <hi>Abſolon</hi> my ſonne, my ſonne. Nothing can be dearer vnto a man then his ſonne, except it be his ſoule. <hi>Hannah</hi> begd a man childe of God,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Sa. 1.11.27.</note> and ſhe had her petition giuen. <hi>Pithius Bithinius</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his ſonne murthered by <hi>Xerxes,</hi> buried him,<note place="margin">Texoff.</note> left his kingdome to his wife, and ſpent the reſt of his life in the ſame graue with him. The <hi>mother</hi> weepeth for the <hi>daughter</hi> as <hi>Rachel</hi> for her children with great mourning;<note place="margin">Mat. 2.18.</note> ſhee brought her children into the world in much <hi>pangs,</hi> to the halfe killing of her ſelfe, yet careth for them to bee <hi>waſhed</hi> and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21375:15"/>
               <hi>ſwadled,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ez. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.4.</note> ſometime <hi>laughing</hi> to hope what they <hi>will be,</hi> ſometimes <hi>diſtreſſed</hi> with feare of what they <hi>may be,</hi> euer tender and deare vnto them, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued in their ſight.<note place="margin">Pro. 4.3.</note> 
               <hi>O that wee were halfe ſo tender of our ſoules as our mothers haue beene of our bodies.</hi> Their teares are ready in life and death. The <hi>ſonne</hi> ſheddeth teares for the <hi>father,</hi> as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> did for <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> when hee had made an end of commanding his ſonnes, gathered vp his feet into the bed, and yeelded vp the ghoſt;<note place="margin">Gen. 50.1. <hi>Muſculus.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ioſeph</hi> fell vpon his face, and wept vpon him, and kiſſed him. It is <hi>Stoicall</hi> to hold that a wiſe man ſhould be without compaſſion or affection.<note place="margin">Gen. 42.24.</note> Hee wept at the ſight of his brethren <hi>aloud,</hi> that the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> and the houſe of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> heard, but his teares were more violent for the death of his <hi>father:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 45.2. Eeel 3.11.</note> no maruell, for the glory of a man is from the honour of his father. The <hi>childe</hi> ſheddeth teares for the death of the <hi>mother,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sara.</note> and perhaps continueth mourning as long as <hi>Izhak</hi> did for his mother,<note place="margin">D. Willet in Gen.</note> 3. yeeres, when ſhee had liued 127. yeeres, the only woman whoſe whole age is recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in Scripture. The <hi>mother</hi> beareth the childe nine moneths in her <hi>womb,</hi> longer in her <hi>armes,</hi> for euer in her <hi>heart:</hi> ſhe beareth with many <hi>childiſh infirmities,</hi> and when no other eye pittieth, ſhee weepeth &amp; <hi>batheth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. ep. de ſuſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto contubernio.</note> &amp; <hi>ſuffereth</hi> much <hi>harty trouble:</hi> ſhee ſo vſeth the children as if they were her <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. conf. l. <hi>9.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> as <hi>A. Auſtin</hi> writeth of the tender affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate care of his mother <hi>Monica</hi> ouer him. The <hi>husband</hi> ſheddeth teares for the death of his <hi>wife,</hi> as <hi>Abraham</hi> who was 140.<note place="margin">Peter.</note> yeeres old at the death of <hi>Sarah:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 2.18.22.</note> man and wife are but one fleſh. The <hi>wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:21375:15"/>was made to be an <hi>helpe</hi> meet for man: ſhee was made of the <hi>ribbe</hi> of man, not from the <hi>earth,</hi> but from the ſide of man; neither out of his <hi>head,</hi> leſt ſhe ſhould be too proud; neither out of his <hi>feet,</hi> for ſhe is not a vaſſall, but from his ſide, that the man knowing the woman to be taken out of him, might more firmely ſet his affection vpon her, being <hi>fleſh</hi> of his fleſh and <hi>bone</hi> of his bones;<note place="margin">Muſe:</note> from his left ſide where his <hi>heart</hi> lay, to ſhew the loue that muſt be betwixt them. It was not of a <hi>monſtrous ſuperfluous</hi> part, but a <hi>ribbe</hi> aboue the vſuall number of ribs, created of purpoſe by the Lord as neceſſary for the creation of woman. A good <hi>wife</hi> is a <hi>conſummation</hi> of other pleaſures:<note place="margin">Calu:</note> 
               <hi>Nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius boni ſine ſocio iucunda eſt poſſeſsio;</hi> No good thing can be poſſeſſed pleaſantly without a companion: no <hi>companion</hi> can be ſo deare to man, which made <hi>Euphrates</hi> a Philoſopher vpon the death of his wife to crie out, O tyrannous <hi>Philoſophie,</hi> thou com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeſt to loue, and if we loſe the things beloued thou forbiddeſt vs to be ſorry for them. The <hi>bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> ſheddeth teares for his brother,<note place="margin">Ber. pro ſi atre Gerardo.</note> as <hi>Bernard</hi> for <hi>Gerardus;</hi> wee were but one heart and one ſoule, but now the ſword hath pierced it, fetching one part to <hi>heauen,</hi> and leauing the other vpon the earth. The <hi>friend</hi> weepeth for the <hi>friend,</hi> as <hi>Christ</hi> did for <hi>Lazarus,</hi> and <hi>Dauid</hi> for <hi>Ionathan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 11.35.</note> I am di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed for thee, very pleaſant haſt thou beene vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mee: and <hi>Gregory Nazianzene</hi> for <hi>Baſil;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Monod. in Baſil.</note> As for my ſelfe, now I am bereaued of ſuch a man, what ſhall I doe, but either die, or liue in miſerie? <hi>which</hi> way ſhall I turne mee? <hi>what</hi> ſhall I doe? <hi>what</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:21375:16"/>counſell ſhall I take, now I haue loſt him that was my comfort? But howſoeuer it bee lawfull to mourne and ſhed teares,<note place="margin">1. Theſſ. 4.13.</note> yet <hi>not as without hope. Mourning</hi> for the dead and remembrance of them is lawfull, elſe <hi>Deborah Rebekkahs</hi> nurſe had not beene buried ſo carefully, and the place expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and called <hi>Allon Bachuth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 35.8. Gen. 35.20.</note> the oake of wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping: elſe <hi>Iacob</hi> had not ſet a pillar vpon the graue of <hi>Rachel,</hi> elſe <hi>Iſrael</hi> had not mourned for <hi>Ioſias,</hi> the faithfull for <hi>Stephen,</hi> and women for <hi>Dorcas. Ennius</hi> the Poet would not be weeped for:</p>
            <q>Nemo me lachrymis decoret,<note place="margin">Tully. Prudent.</note> nec funera fletu.</q>
            <p>No more would <hi>Laurence</hi> the Martyr: but <hi>Solon</hi> commanded that the Common-wealth ſhould mourne for his death, and wee muſt ſhedde ſome teares ouer the dead <hi>Saints, becauſe</hi> by their depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture wee may ſeeme to ſuffer harmes:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ecc.</hi> 38.16.</note> we had <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort</hi> by their preſence, which we want by their ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, <hi>becauſe</hi> they did much good to the Church and Common-wealth. The <hi>world</hi> was bleſſed by them; <hi>worſe</hi> vſually ſucceed: the <hi>wicked</hi> will grow more obſtinate, and wee may <hi>feare</hi> ſome iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to follow:<note place="margin">Iſ. 57.1.</note> for their <hi>death</hi> is a prognoſtication of ſome euill to come; as when <hi>Noah</hi> entred into the Arke, the world was drowned with the floud; and when <hi>Lot</hi> departed out of <hi>Sodome,</hi> it was burnt. The godly need not to feare as <hi>Herod,</hi> who being ready to die,<note place="margin">Ioſ. ant. l. <hi>17.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi> &amp; de bello Iud. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> and thinking that his death would be a ioy to many, ſhut vp in priſon ſome Noble men of euery Towne, and required his ſiſter <hi>Salome</hi> and her husband <hi>Alexa,</hi> that as ſoone as bee was dead they ſhould kill thoſe Noble men,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:21375:16"/>and then all <hi>Indaea</hi> would lament his death. The Lord cauſeth them to be lamented, as he did <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> in <hi>Italie, Auſtin</hi> in <hi>Africke, Luther</hi> in <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie,</hi> and others in other places, ſending extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary iudgements immediately after their deaths. But our comfort ſhould bee, as <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">Cyp:</note> 
               <hi>that</hi> they are but gone before, and wee ſhall follow after: that we muſt not <hi>lament</hi> them ouer-much, who by the <hi>call</hi> of God are freed from miſerie: <hi>that</hi> they are but gone a iourney, wee muſt looke for their returne; <hi>they</hi> are ſailed into a ſtrange coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and will if wee wait come againe; <hi>that</hi> their deaths are not <hi>funerals,</hi> but <hi>triumphs;</hi> that as life without <hi>Chriſt</hi> is death,<note place="margin">Ignat:</note> ſo their death with and in <hi>Chriſt</hi> is life; that loue commandeth our <hi>teares,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſid:</note> but faith ſhould rule our <hi>paſsions,</hi> and preſcribe a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration; that as <hi>Ierome</hi> ſpake to <hi>Euſtochium</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning her mother <hi>Paula,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. ad Euſtoch. Epitaph. Paula.</note> we ſhould not ſo much mourne becauſe we haue loſt ſuch, as giue thanks that wee haue had ſuch, yea rather that wee ſtill haue ſuch, for all liue vnto God, and whoſoeuer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turneth vnto the Lord is reckoned in the number of the familie; <hi>that</hi> we ſhall all meet at the laſt and there ſhall bee no more occaſion of ſorrowing, ſighing, ſobbing; for as the <hi>ſpirit</hi> here telleth <hi>Saint Iohn,</hi> when wee appeare before the Lambe, <hi>God</hi> ſhall wipe away all teares, and there ſhall bee no more occaſion of mourning: which directeth to this doctrinall propoſition,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That after the end of this life God will free all the elect from all miſeries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is prophecied of by <hi>Eſay, c.</hi> 57.2.<note place="margin">Doct.</note> He ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21375:17"/>into peace, they ſhall reſt in their beds, each one walking in his vprightneſſe: ſo in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 126.5.6. They that ſow in teares ſhall reape in ioy. He that goeth forth and <hi>weepeth,</hi> bearing <hi>pretious ſeede,</hi> ſhall doubtleſſe come againe with <hi>reioycing,</hi> bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his <hi>ſheaues</hi> with him: a <hi>truth</hi> repeated <hi>c.</hi> 21. of this prophecie <hi>v.</hi> 4. And <hi>God</hi> ſhall wipe away all teares from their eyes, and there ſhall be no more <hi>death,</hi> neither <hi>ſorrow,</hi> nor <hi>crying,</hi> neither ſhall there be any more <hi>paine:</hi> for the former things are paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed away. Here <hi>teares</hi> often are helpfull to expell griefe: as the Poet deſired to be wept for, it would doe him a pleaſure.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Fle que meos caſus,<note place="margin">On: l. <hi>4.</hi> Triſt.</note> eſt quaedam ſlere voluptas:</l>
               <l>Expletur lachrymis, egeriturque dolor.</l>
            </q>
            <p>But hereafter there ſhall be no occaſion of teares: as was to <hi>Ioſiah</hi> weeping at the denouncing of a curſe,<note place="margin">2 King. 22.19. 2. King. 20.3. Neh. 1.3.</note> to <hi>Hezekiah</hi> weeping ſore at a meſſage of death, to <hi>Nehemiah</hi> weeping becauſe the wall of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> was broken downe, and the gates there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of burnt with fire,<note place="margin">Iob 30.25. Iſ 22.4. Ier 9.1.</note> to <hi>Iob</hi> for him that was in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and the poore, to <hi>Iſai</hi> for the ſpoiling of the daughter of his people, to <hi>Ieremie</hi> for the ſlaine of the daughter of his people, to <hi>Eliſha</hi> the man of God weeping for Iſrael, whoſe ſtrong holds were to be ſet on fire, their young men to be ſlaine with the ſword, their children to bee daſhed, and their women with childe ript;<note place="margin">2 King 8.12.</note> to <hi>Phaltiel</hi> weeping be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his wife <hi>Michol</hi> was ſent for away from him by <hi>Iſhboſheth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 3.16. Gen. 21.16.</note> to <hi>Hagar</hi> when all the water was ſpent in the bottle, and ſhee caſt her childe vnder the ſhrubs, and ſate downe a good way off, as it were
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:21375:17"/>a bow ſhoot, that ſhee might not ſee the death of her child:<note place="margin">Mat. 26.75.</note> or to <hi>Peter</hi> weeping bitterly for deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Maſter. The way of all holy <hi>Kings, Prophets, Apoſtles, Martyrs, Confeſſors,</hi> and <hi>Saints</hi> hath beene by the weeping croſſe. Their <hi>colours</hi> haue bin per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions. <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath beene perſecuted,<note place="margin">Iohn 25.20.</note> ſo muſt they be. Their combatings are their many affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, but <hi>the Lord deliuereth them out of all.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 34.19.</note> They performe no <hi>deuotion</hi> more pleaſing to God then their hearty teares which they poure out ſo plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, that they cauſe their <hi>beds</hi> to ſwimme in teares, to be their <hi>meate</hi> day and night,<note place="margin">Pſam. 6.6.</note> and to be <hi>botled</hi> vp by God himſelfe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 42 3.</note> who <hi>ſhall wipe them all away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vſe</hi> 1.</note>How <hi>terrible</hi> is this meſſage to the obdurate ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners that neuer ſhed teares for ſinne:<note place="margin">Bar.</note> For <hi>Deus non infundit oleum miſericordiae niſi in vas contritum,</hi> God poures not the oyle of his mercy, but into a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken veſſell. The <hi>obſtinate</hi> ſinner hath no teares and therefore can hereafter haue no comfort.<note place="margin">Ier. 19 10.</note> They are not humbled vnto this day: Chriſt wept for the ſinnes of others, but theſe will not weepe for their owne. <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhed his bloud for the leaſt ſins, but they ſhedde not one drop of water for the greateſt ſinne:<note place="margin">Eccl 12 5.</note> they are worſe then thoſe hired <hi>mourners</hi> going about the ſtreetes which would lament and cut themſeleus and make themſelues bald for a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle reward, making this their whole trade.</p>
            <q>Vt flerent oculos crudiêre ſuos.</q>
            <p>But <hi>Heauen</hi> cannot drawe theſe, worſe then the <hi>Hart,</hi> for if he be compaſſed with dogges,<note place="margin">Pliny.</note> he will weepe and mourne, but theſe will not though ſet about by many ſinnes and as many <hi>Diuels.</hi> No ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:21375:18"/>can be accepted without an humble heart, vnleſſe a man hath a <hi>poore,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 66.3.</note> a <hi>contrite,</hi> a <hi>trembling</hi> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, if he kill an <hi>Oxe</hi> he is as if he ſlew a man, if he ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice a <hi>Lambe,</hi> it <hi>is as if he cut off a dogges necke,</hi> if he offer an oblation, it is as if hee offered <hi>ſwines</hi> bloud, if he burne incenſe, it is as if hee bleſſed an idoll,<note place="margin">Amb. de paeni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>our prayers muſt haue teares, God</hi> expecteth them that he may ſend reliefe. This is our violence that we muſt offer to the <hi>Lord. Prayer</hi> doth molli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, but teares doe compell.<note place="margin">Aug. Ser.</note> 
               <hi>Exhortations</hi> to others muſt haue teares. If we would haue them to weep, we muſt ſhed teares our ſelues, therefore <hi>Origen</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his fall taking that text, and reading it in the Church:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.16.</note> 
               <hi>But vnto the wicked God ſaith,</hi> what haſt thou to doe to declare my ſtatutes, or that thou ſhouldeſt take my couenant in thy mouth, ſeeing thou hateſt inſtruction, and caſteſt my words be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind thee: being not able to ſpeake for teares ſet all the congregation a crying, ſo effectuall is the ſilence of a <hi>touched</hi> weeping heart: the <hi>Saints</hi> haue grace in their words and in their very faces.<note place="margin">Chryſ.</note> Heare the word neuer ſo zealouſly, yet vnleſſe thy heart be melted, it is but like the ſtrokes of an hammer vpon an anuile. But if with <hi>Dauid</hi> we make a <hi>Bath</hi> of our teares, a <hi>Cauldron</hi> of our bed, an <hi>Altar</hi> of our heart, a <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> not of vnreaſonable beaſts, but of our owne bodies, a liuing and reaſonable ſacrifice, we ſhall haue comfort hereafter: Haſt thou beene <hi>omnium notarum peccator,</hi> a ſinner ſoyled with eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſinne, be now then <hi>omnium horarum paenitens,</hi> a penitentiary euery houte for ſinne: weepe for thy ſelfe, and after for the ſinnes of others, elſe thou
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21375:18"/>muſt immediately after this life is ended bee caſt into that place where there ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of teeth: <hi>Woe</hi> be vnto thee if thou doeſt nothing but laugh, <hi>it ſhall be turned into mourning. Mourning</hi> for friends cannot raiſe them againe, though men ſhould weepe their eyes out of the holes of their heads,<note place="margin">Chryſ. ad pop. Antioch, hem. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> but <hi>godly ſorrow</hi> for ſinne will helpe, and purchaſe vs that which <hi>Achſah</hi> got of her Father <hi>Caleb,</hi> the vpper and the nether ſprings,<note place="margin">Ioſ. 15 19.</note> a ſpring of comfort heere, and heereafter a ſpring of the water of life: <hi>all teares ſhall be wiped away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vſe</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>Here</hi> then may the <hi>thirſty ſoule come and drinke freely of this comfort: God</hi> helpeth the mourners with his owne hand: Neuer did <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> ſo much honor vnto groaning <hi>Virgil</hi> and bleare-eyed <hi>Horace,</hi> as God to the pooreſt of his mourners, wiping away all their teares: <hi>He breaketh not a brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed reede, he quencheth not ſmoking flaxe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 12.20.</note> The more humble &amp; ſorrowfull we are before him, the nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer wee come vnto him, worldly <hi>ſorrow</hi> bringeth <hi>gray</hi> haires on the head, and <hi>wrinckles</hi> in the face, but a godly weeping turneth <hi>old age</hi> into youth, &amp; <hi>ſickneſſe</hi> into health: Behold how they wrought a miracle for <hi>Mary Magdalene,</hi> ſhee is called a <hi>wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> ſhee is not named <hi>eyther</hi> for her honour,<note place="margin">Luk. 7.37.38.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe as Chriſt couered her ſins, ſo the Scripture concealeth her name: or for her diſhonor, as if ſhe were not worth the naming: <hi>ſomtimes</hi> the name of ſinners is vſed with an abbreuiation <hi>Dumah</hi> for <hi>Idu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 21.11.</note> 
               <hi>Ram</hi> for <hi>Aram, Paſdammim</hi> for <hi>Epheſdammim,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ruth. 4.19.</note> ſometimes their name is concealed, as in that reall parable of the condemned <hi>churle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Ch. 11.13. 1. Sam. 17.1.</note> his title is but <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:21375:19"/>quidam diues: Herod</hi> hath no other name allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed then a <hi>Fox,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 16.19. Luk 13.32. Amos 4.1.</note> the <hi>Princes</hi> which oppreſſed the poore, <hi>Kine of Baſhan</hi> in the mountains of <hi>Samaria.</hi> or ſhee is nameleſſe to teach men that howſoeuer they heere ſtriue to make their houſes continue for euer, and their dwelling places to all generations, calling their lands after their own names,<note place="margin">Pſal. 49.11.</note> yet God remembreth them not: Shee was a <hi>cittie ſinner,</hi> which had added <hi>wound</hi> to wound, <hi>corruption</hi> to corruption, <hi>ſtench</hi> to ſtench: In <hi>that</hi> citty where <hi>Chriſt</hi> had raiſed the <hi>widdowes</hi> ſon, doth ſhe expect ſaluation, ſhee came with an <hi>Alablaſter</hi> boxe of oyntment wherewith ſhee vſed before to perfume her ſelfe; or leaſt by the ſtench of her ſinnes ſhee ſhould offend her Sauiour, or to prepare him with a gift, ſhee ſtood at his <hi>feete</hi> behind him weeping, waſhing his feete with teares, ſhee <hi>feared</hi> puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and therefore ſtood behind; ſhe <hi>waſhed</hi> with teares, By diuine grace ſhee opened the <hi>conduits</hi> and ſluces of her eyes, ſhee <hi>bewailed</hi> all her ſinnes, ſhe <hi>wiped</hi> his feete with the haire of her head: Her ſinnes which were many were forgiuen, for ſhe lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued much.<note place="margin">Verſ 47. <hi>Bar. Annal.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Baronius</hi> ſaith, hee found in an old ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuſcript that ſhe came with <hi>Lazarus</hi> and her ſiſter <hi>Martha</hi> into Britaine: If it be ſo, her <hi>example</hi> is more proper for vs of great Britaine: Happy are they that follow the ſmell of this oyntment and the teares of that little vine: For as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his chariots were drowned the red ſea, there remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned not ſo much as one of them: ſo the ſpirituall <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and all his ſtratagems ſhall be drowned in the Sea of our teares:<note place="margin">Exod 14.28.</note> 
               <hi>Illi in fluctibus, iſti infletibus,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21375:19"/>marini illi amari iſti:</hi> The <hi>Aegyptian Pharaoh</hi> and his Chariots were drowned in the ſalt waues of the red Sea, ſo all our croſſes ſhall bee drowned in the ſalt teares of our eyes,<note place="margin">Ber. ſer. <hi>39</hi> in Cant.</note> which are made red with weeping. Let then ſome hold weeping to be chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh, wee can neuer enter into the kingdome of heauen, except wee become in this like little <hi>chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</hi> Let others thinke that the cuſtome of ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding teares, <hi>daſheth</hi> all ioy as they in the Poet:</p>
            <q>Parcite lachrimis vrbis feſto laetoque die.<note place="margin">Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. in Octauia.</note>
            </q>
            <p>Wee can neuer be truly cheerefull, vnleſſe wee accuſtome our ſelues to theſe. Let other thinke that it is their greateſt diſhonour to be buried pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uately, as it is ſtoried of <hi>Clodius,</hi> that hee was caſt out, <hi>ſine imaginibus, ſine cantu, ſine ludis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ic. pro Milon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>ſine exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quijs, ſine lamentis,</hi> without any ſolemnization of his memory by picture, ſong, play, funerall, or mourning: but this is the heauieſt of all plagues to haue drie hearts that cannot melt, that are ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of no true ſorrow. The watry <hi>eye</hi> is the ſureſt of continuance vpon earth, and ſhall bee ſurely glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in heauen, as theſe laſt words manifeſt that God ſhall wipe away all teares, <hi>from their eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pars</hi> 3.</note>IN that <hi>prophecie</hi> of <hi>Iacob,</hi> when hee told his Sons what ſhould befall them in the laſt daies, <hi>God</hi> had this bleſſing: <hi>A troope ſhall ouercome him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen 49.19.</note> 
               <hi>but he
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:21375:20"/>ſhall ouercome at the laſt:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 49.19.</note> which is not to bee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of <hi>Iephte</hi> his good ſucceſſe againſt the <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monites</hi> as <hi>Caietan</hi> would haue it, neyther of the <hi>Gadites</hi> marching with the reſt of the tribes againſt the <hi>Canaanites,</hi> and there returning back to <hi>Iordan,</hi> as <hi>Ierom</hi> and the <hi>Chaldee</hi> Paraphraſt defend, but of the diuers conflicts which the <hi>Gadites</hi> had with the <hi>Hagarens,</hi>
               <note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. &amp; Mecar.</note> with <hi>Iehur</hi> and <hi>Nephiſh,</hi> and <hi>Nodah</hi> when they carried away of their Camels 50. thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, and of Sheepe 250. thouſand, and of Aſſes two thouſand,<note place="margin">1. Chr. 5.21.</note> and of men an hundred thouſand. It is true of all the <hi>elect</hi> who ſeeme heere to bee deie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and ouercome by croſſes, ſorrowes, &amp; teares: for the world holdeth that <hi>vita non eſt viuere ſed valere:</hi> It is more comfortable to dye quickly then to liue ſickly. Search we the Scriptures, wee ſhall find ſome <hi>Lepers</hi> who were to liue alone, and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked out by <hi>torne</hi> garments, <hi>bare</hi> heads, <hi>couered</hi> mouthes and an <hi>outcry of vncleanneſſe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leu. 13.45.</note> 
               <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> was lame of his feete by falling from his nurſe as ſhe made haſt to flye.<note place="margin">1. Sam. 4.4.</note> In the time of <hi>Chriſt</hi> you ſhal finde one deafe and hauing an impediment in his ſpeech;<note place="margin">Mark. 7.32.</note> another <hi>Lazar</hi> lying at <hi>Diues</hi> gate; another at the poole of <hi>Betheſda;</hi> another at the beautifull gate of the Temple: you ſhall find heere a <hi>woman</hi> whoſe yong <hi>daughter</hi> had an vnclean ſpirit, there a <hi>women</hi> with a <hi>bloudy iſſue:</hi> here the houſe <hi>vntiled</hi> by the ſicke of the <hi>Palſie</hi> his porters, there the <hi>graues</hi> haunted by men poſſeſſed of <hi>Diuels, Neſcias vltrum appelles vitam mortalem, an mortalem vitam:</hi> We can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſaith S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> tell what to call our life, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a dying life or a liuing death: but amongſt all
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:21375:20"/>infirmities the want of ſight maketh many to cry as <hi>Tobit</hi> in his blindneſſe when hee could not goe without ſtumbling,<note place="margin">Tob. 11.10.</note> hauing white filmes vpon his eyes which the <hi>Phyſitians</hi> could not cure: com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand my <hi>ſpirit</hi> to be taken from me, that I may be diſſolued and become earth, for it is profitable for me to die rather then to liue. But ſaith <hi>Auguſt:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tob. 3.6. <hi>Aug. conf.</hi> 10.34.</note> O the light which <hi>Tobias</hi> ſaw, when his carnal eies being ſhut, he ſet his ſon notwithſtanding into the right way of life, and trod out a direct path before him as a guide. <hi>Blinde men</hi> may bee and often are neceſſary to the Church and Common-wealth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Izhak, Ge.</hi> 27.1</note> and therefore God hath made way for them, and forbidden <hi>a ſtumbling blocke</hi> to bee put before them.<note place="margin">Leu. 19.4.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Plut in vita Coriolani.</note>The <hi>Romans</hi> impoſed vpon ſome of their chiefe Families the ſurnames of <hi>Coeci</hi> and <hi>Claudi,</hi> blinde and lame, that the people ſhould not ſcorne at thoſe imperfections, and contemne excellent gifts of the minde reſiding in ſuch bodies. So did <hi>Lewes</hi> the eight of that name thinke, inſtituting a <hi>Colledge</hi> of three hundred blinde men, vpon occaſion that ſo many of his ſouldiers were taken in warres a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Moores,</hi> and ſent home with their eyes put out, which Colledge ſtandeth to this day in <hi>Paris,</hi> and deuoted to the ſame vſe. So did iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious <hi>Hottoman</hi> affirme that blinde men may ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie the places of <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>quaeſt. il<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſt q. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> though blinde from their birth. And <hi>Seneca</hi> of <hi>Prieſthood,</hi> propoſing the queſtion whether <hi>Metellus</hi> a Prieſt,<note place="margin">Sen. l. <hi>4.</hi> contr. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> who was become blinde, could notwithſtanding retaine the Prieſthood, ſalueth the doubt, that <hi>Lex inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grum
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:21375:21"/>grum ad animum refert, non ad corpus,</hi> the Law loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to the blindneſſe of the minde, not of the body. They may be famous in many things for all their blindneſſe, elſe blinde <hi>Iſacius</hi> and <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> the ſixt amongſt Emperours, <hi>Robert Waucop</hi> a <hi>Scot</hi> by birth among Archbiſhops,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Carion Ann.</hi> 1551. Corpus Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti Coll. in Oxford.</note> 
               <hi>Fox</hi> an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Founder of a flouriſhing Colledge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Biſhops, venerable <hi>Bedt</hi> and <hi>Zanchie</hi> that purely-refined Schooleman among Schoolemen, <hi>Lycurgus</hi> among Law-giuers, <hi>Ziſca</hi> among Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals had neuer beene ſo famous:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>D. Hakewill</hi> in his learned Treatiſe of the vantie of the eye.</note> elſe <hi>Philip, Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibal, Antigonus</hi> and <hi>Sartorius</hi> had poſſeſſed more then foure eyes: <hi>Appius Claudius</hi> for a Stateſman, <hi>Caius Druſius</hi> for a Lawyer, <hi>Thamyra</hi> and <hi>Steſiche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> for Poets, <hi>Aufidius Pratorius</hi> for a Hiſtorio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grapher,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tuſe.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>Dioderus</hi> the Stoike, who liued in <hi>Tullies</hi> owne houſe, for a Mathematician, <hi>Didymus</hi> for a Preacher,<note place="margin">Ier. ep. <hi>33.</hi> ad Caſtrutium. Granaten in Luc. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> whom <hi>Anthony</hi> perſwaded not to bee grieued for the loſſe of thoſe eyes which were common to him with flies, and mice, and gnats, but rather reioyce in thoſe which were proper to Saints and Angels. Theſe are proofes that the want of corporall eyes doth not debarre men of happineſſe:<note place="margin">Paſſeratius de coetitate.</note> nay to many it is <hi>diuinum bonum,</hi> a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine good thing, albeit <hi>humanum malum,</hi> a ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming euill to men. But the <hi>eyes</hi> of the godly, though now neuer ſo dimme and bleare, ſhall bee cleared with Gods owne hand, when once we ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare before him, and then ſhall wee haue no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content.</p>
            <p>So that wee may ſafely faſten vpon this laſt leſſon:</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:21375:21"/>
               <hi>That no member or part of man ſhall bee vnglorified by God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Doct.</note> 
               <hi>but eſpecially the eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The reſolution of many <hi>Saints</hi> proueth this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. Was not this the reſtoratiue of the fainting ſoule of <hi>Iob,</hi> the <hi>bleſsing</hi> and <hi>ſappe</hi> in the vine of the deadeſt winter of affliction, the <hi>couch</hi> to lodge his diſtreſſed &amp; diſeaſed bones vpon, his <hi>helper</hi> when his wife moleſted him, and his beſt <hi>friend</hi> when his friends forſooke him? Did not he call for the <hi>enrol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of this happy argument, <hi>for bookes</hi> of the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt continuance, and pens, the bookes to bee of <hi>lead</hi> in the rocke for euer, and his <hi>pen</hi> of <hi>iron?</hi> Though after my skinne wormes deſtroy this bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,<note place="margin">Iob <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9:26.27.</note> yet in my fleſh ſhall I ſee God, <hi>whom I ſhall ſee for my ſelfe, and mine eyes ſhall behold.</hi> He knew for earthly matters that after his <hi>diſſolution</hi> his eye ſhould no more ſee God,<note place="margin">Iob 7.7.8.</note> that the eye of him that ſaw him ſhould ſee him no more, <hi>i.</hi> to returne to earth, but hee ſhould ſee God. In his extremitie he wiſhed that no eye had ſeene him;<note place="margin">10 18.</note> his eye was dimme by reaſon of ſorrow,<note place="margin">17.7.</note> and all his members were but as a ſhadow; this was his comfort, that God would <hi>one day</hi> glorifie him. This made him to couenant with his <hi>eyes, to be eyes to the blinde,</hi>
               <note place="margin">31.1. 29.15. 16.20 Pſal. 119 82.18.</note> and with his <hi>eye</hi> to poure out teares vnto God when his friends ſcorned him. This cauſed <hi>Dauid</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe vnto God, Mine <hi>eyes</hi> falle for thy word, ſaying, when wilt thou comfort me? and to pray, <hi>Open thou mine eyes.</hi> There ore <hi>Chriſt</hi> praying God for his power at the graue of <hi>Lazarus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh 11.41. 17.1.</note> lifted vp his eyes, as hee did a little before hee was betrayed. This cauſed <hi>S. Paul</hi> to pray for the <hi>Epheſians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.18.</note> that
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:21375:22"/>the eyes of their vnderſtanding might bee inlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, to know the hope of their calling, and the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the glory of his inheritance. The <hi>eyes</hi> of the body are opened three wayes, <hi>either</hi> when the blinde are made to ſee, as <hi>Chriſt</hi> cauſed <hi>Bartimaeus</hi> to ſee, or when he that hath eyes ſeeth more then hee ſaw, as <hi>Balaam</hi> ſaw the Angell, <hi>or</hi> when they which ſee diſcerne that which they perceiued not before, as the <hi>Diſciples</hi> diſcerned <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of bread: ſo are the <hi>eyes</hi> of the minde <hi>when</hi> we are brought from ignorance to the knowledge of Chriſt, <hi>when</hi> wee are brought by affliction to know our ſelues, as the <hi>prodigall, when</hi> a mans ſinne preſenteth it ſelfe vpon the committing of it, as to <hi>Adam,</hi> and to <hi>Iudas.</hi> But our <hi>eyes</hi> at the laſt ſhall bee open to ſee God as hee is,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.2. Pſal. 27.13.</note> and to bee glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied: <hi>without</hi> this refreſhing wee are euer ready to faint.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vſe</hi> 1.</note>Which ſtriketh <hi>horrour</hi> into the hearts of repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates:<note place="margin">Iob 21.17.</note> for their <hi>candle</hi> ſhall bee put out, and God ſhall diſtribute ſorrowes vnto them in his anger. They admit nothing but poiſon into their <hi>eyes,</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>couetouſneſſe,</hi> when hauing neither childe nor brother, yet there is no end of their labour, neither is their eye ſatisfied with riches;<note place="margin">Eccl. 4.8. 2. Pet. 2.14. Gen. 39.7.</note> or of <hi>adulterie,</hi> that cannot ceaſe from ſinne, as <hi>Puti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phars</hi> wife caſt her eyes vpon <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Lie with mee;</hi> or of <hi>drunkenneſſe</hi> looking vpon the <hi>wine</hi> when it is redde,<note place="margin">Pro. 23.31. Mat. 20.15. <hi>Aug. l.</hi> 3. <hi>de gen. ad lit. c.</hi> 24.</note> and giueth his <hi>colour in the cuppe;</hi> or of <hi>enuie,</hi> their eyes are euill becauſe the eyes of other are <hi>good. The eye ſet apart from the other parts of the body, is faire and well fauoured in
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:21375:22"/>it ſelfe. Orpheus</hi> called it the looking-glaſſe of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>Aphrodiſeus</hi> the caſement of the ſoule, <hi>Ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor</hi> the Arabian too too grofly, the manſion of the ſoule. But how ſubiect is it to infirmities and diſeaſes? <hi>Charron</hi> reckoneth 120.<note place="margin">L. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>11.</hi> de Sap. L. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Coelius Rhodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginus</hi> many more, <hi>Laurentius</hi> durſt not vndertake to number them, but we may ſumme vp all with that leſſon: <hi>Death entreth in at the windowes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 9 21. Pſal 112.10.</note> The <hi>eyes</hi> of many are full of <hi>malice,</hi> grieuing at the good of others; of <hi>gluttonie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 31.14. <hi>Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e</hi>
               </note> ſtretching whitherſoeuer they looke; eyes of <hi>pride</hi> and ſuperſtition, behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Sunne when it ſhineth,<note place="margin">Iob 31 26.</note> and the Moone walking in brightneſſe; eyes of <hi>idolatrie,</hi> to looke vpon images, and after theſe to goe a whoring:<note place="margin">Num. 15 39. Eccl. 31.13.</note> ſo that <hi>nothing is created more wicked then an eye. therefore it weepeth vpon euery occaſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Heathens</hi> dedicated the <hi>eares</hi> to <hi>Minerua,</hi> the <hi>tongue</hi> to <hi>Mercury,</hi> the <hi>armes</hi> to <hi>Neptune,</hi> and the <hi>eye</hi> to <hi>Cupid;</hi> but now luſt draweth all other ſinnes by the eyes. To all ſuch who tremble not to behold with the ſame <hi>eyes</hi> with which they looke vpon their <hi>adulterous beds,</hi> lying idols, and ſuch like, the <hi>ſacred Table</hi> where the Sacrament is performed, <hi>who</hi> enter into the Church not loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to their affections, <hi>who</hi> labour not for good eyes, I muſt ſay as <hi>Chriſt</hi> doth, <hi>If their eye be euill, their whole body ſhall bee full of darkneſſe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt 6.23.</note> as is their ſenſe of ſinne, ſo and much more heere after ſhall bee their ſenſe of ſorrow. Their <hi>eyes</hi> ſhall faile, and they ſhall not eſcape,<note place="margin">Iob 11.20.</note> and their <hi>hope</hi> ſhall bee as the giuing vp of the ghoſt. The <hi>light</hi> is ſweet, but they muſt goe to darkneſſe,<note place="margin">Eccl. 11 8.</note> for euer
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:21375:23"/>to houle there, when the elect ſhall haue <hi>all teares wiped away from their eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vſe</hi> 2.</note>A <hi>Medicine</hi> then hence may bee applied to all ſickneſſes, a <hi>ſalue</hi> to euery ſore, and a <hi>plaiſter</hi> for euery wound,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.53.</note> 
               <hi>that</hi> wee ſhall bee thus changed, <hi>that</hi> this corruptible muſt put on incorruption, and this <hi>mortall</hi> muſt put on <hi>immortalitie,</hi> that our <hi>vile</hi> ſhall bee a <hi>glorious</hi> body, that there ſhall bee no more ſinging of <hi>Lachrymae,</hi> but of <hi>Hoſanna</hi> and <hi>Halcluiah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was the encouragement of God vnto <hi>Iacob</hi> in his going downe into <hi>Aegypt:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 46 4.</note> 
               <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſhall put his hand vpon thine <hi>eyes:</hi> it is to bee vnderſtood of <hi>Ioſephs cloſing his eyes when hee had giuen vp the ghoſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Muſe:</note> Men commonly in dying open and <hi>lift</hi> vp their eyes to <hi>heauen:</hi> and this duty is performed by thoſe who are deareſt and beſt beloued of the dead, as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was of <hi>Iacob:</hi> but behold <hi>Gods</hi> owne hand is heere promiſed to bee vpon our <hi>eyes,</hi> to wipe from them all teares, and then wee ſhall ſee the <hi>glory</hi> prouided. Hee giueth a <hi>taſte</hi> of it to ſome in this life, neuer ſuffering them to depart comfortleſſe.<note place="margin">Num. 27.12.20.28.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaw the land of promiſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he died, <hi>Aaron</hi> his ſonne <hi>Eleazer</hi> in his roome before hee died, <hi>Dauid Salomon</hi> his ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour before hee died, <hi>Ezekias</hi> his houſe in order, <hi>Chriſt</hi> his <hi>transfiguration</hi> on the mount. <hi>Stephen</hi> ſaw the <hi>heauens</hi> opened,<note place="margin">Act 7 56.</note> and the ſonne of man ſtanding on the right hand of God. Thus had <hi>M. Deering</hi> a taſte a little before his death, being raiſed vp in his bed, ſeeing the Sunne ſhine, and being deſired to ſpeake, ſaid: <hi>There is but one Sunne
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:21375:23"/>that giueth light to the world, but one righteouſneſſe, one communion of Saints: As concerning death, I feele ſuch ioy of ſpirit, that if I ſhould haue the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of life on the one ſide, and the ſentence of death on the other ſide, I had rather chuſe a thouſand times (ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God hath appointed the ſeparation) the ſentence of death then the ſentence of life.</hi> Thus had <hi>another</hi> holy <hi>Saint</hi> a taſte of it a little before death:<note place="margin">M. Iohn Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</note> 
               <hi>What brightneſſe doe I ſee?</hi> and being told it was the <hi>Sunne ſhine,</hi> Nay, ſaith hee, <hi>my Sauiour ſhines: Now farewell world, welcome heauen: The day ſtarre from on high hath viſited my heart: Preach it at my funerall: God dealeth familiarly with man, I feele his mercy, I ſee his maieſtie, whether in the body, or out of the body, I cannot tell, God hee knoweth, but I ſee things that are vnutterable.</hi> How much more <hi>happy</hi> then are they that are diſſolued from the fleſh, that <hi>depart</hi> hence in the Lord, that bee in <hi>ioy</hi> and felicitie, that <hi>reſt</hi> from their labours, that haue all <hi>teares wiped away from their eyes.</hi> O then let <hi>mourning</hi> and <hi>teares</hi> bee our <hi>marke</hi> and <hi>badge,</hi> whether wee looke vpward to <hi>God</hi> whom wee haue offended, or downeward vpon <hi>hell</hi> which wee haue deſerued, or backward vpon our <hi>ſinnes</hi> committed, or forward vpon <hi>iudgements</hi> to bee feared, or without vs vpon the deceitfull <hi>world</hi> which wee haue loued, or within vs vpon our <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> polluted. The <hi>Spirit</hi> helpeth our infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,<note place="margin">Rom 8.26.</note> and if wee ſhed teares heere of <hi>contrition</hi> till wee know that our ſinnes are <hi>forgiuen</hi> vs, teares of <hi>deuotion</hi> for that ſudden ioy we receiue from God, teares of <hi>compaſsion</hi> for the wants of others; wee
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:21375:24"/>ſhall <hi>eat</hi> when the wicked ſhall be hungry, <hi>drinke</hi> when they bee thirſtie, <hi>reioyce</hi> when they ſhall be aſhamed, <hi>ſing</hi> for ioy of heart when they ſhall cry for ſorrow of heart, and ſhall houle for vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſpirit.<note place="margin">If. 65.13.14.</note> 
               <hi>Thus ſhall God euen our owne God bleſſe vs. To him and his Sonne and Spirit be glory for euer.</hi> AMEN.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
